{
  "reference_number": "2090",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "Time is of the essence, but the best route is to have the Climate Commission to advise the policy process."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "CO2 is the key gas as it has such a long lifetime. we must get CO2 concentrations at least stabilised if we are to have any hope of\n avoiding very serious changes in the climate, and multi-metre sea level rise. Recent research shows that short-lived gases such as\n\n methane can be stabilised, to stop growing their warming effect. This is sufficient in the short term (next 30 years) but the short-lived\n gases must come down eventually. It would be good to see policy that focuses most strongly on carbon dioxide, but has a reduction\n target for methane and other GHGs (notably nitrous oxide) as well."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We need real emissions reductions, in NZ. This is an opportunity to lead the world."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should be an option to strengthen the target(s), but not weaken them."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, generally, provided there is also a hard target date for zero CO2 emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "If there were technological breakthroughs, or catastrophic extreme events, the government should have the flexibility to take action\n\nto tighten budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, generally, though the potential costs of inaction, or weak action, must be properly considered against short-term costs of action.\nTax relief etc should be factored in for lower-income groups."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Climate change affects us all, and will seriously damage our way of life if we don't take decisive collective action, based on mutual\n\nunderstanding of the risks. The whole of our society should be informed and consulted, as far as is practicable."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Commission should be the vehicle for advising government, and for monitoring progress, publicly. It should not have decision-\nmaking powers. However, there needs to be a mechanism to ensure governments respond appropriately and fully to Commission\nrecommendations."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Broadly, but ensure high-quality climate science expertise. Someone with political science knowledge would also be an asset."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation is critical, as we have already set in train significant changes. Coastal property owners, for instance, cannot be left hung\n\nout to dry when insurance companies stop covering their risk."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Sounds good. The more communication, and the more transparency around what's going on, the better."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I am excited by the setting up of the Commission, and the zero-carbon bill. Done well, we have the opportunity to make a real\ndifference to the future of NZ and the world, in the face of the biggest challenge humanity has ever faced. I have just participated in\n\nthe first Lead Author meeting for the 6th Assessment Report of the IPCC, and I am reminded strongly of the stakes, the level of\ncommitment already at play, and the urgency of action."
    }
  ]
}
